<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
	<title>Linn Abraham&#39;s homepage</title>
	<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/</link>
	<description>Recent content in Selecteds on Linn Abraham&#39;s homepage</description>
	<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
	<language>en-us</language>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 12:40:39 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://linnabraham.me/selected/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	
	
	<item>
		<title>Vim Tips</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/notes/vim_tips/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 15:04:48 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/notes/vim_tips/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-useful-plugins-to-use-with-vim&#34;&gt;Some Useful Plugins to use with ViM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gruvbox - A better colortheme than the default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;markdown-preview - Preview markdown in vim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vimtex - Use vim as LaTeX editor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-gnupg - Handle gpg encrypted files easily with vim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Git and related concepts</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/git_and_related/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 12:40:39 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/selected/git_and_related/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;diff&#34;&gt;Diff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See my notes on &lt;a href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/notes/understanding_diff/&#34;&gt;Understanding Diff&lt;/a&gt;.
To see the changes that are brought about by a particular commit in git, do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git diff &amp;lt;parent-commit&amp;gt;..&amp;lt;current-commit&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;add---patch&#34;&gt;Add &amp;ndash;patch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use the &lt;code&gt;git add&lt;/code&gt; command with the &lt;code&gt;-p&lt;/code&gt; option to stage specific hunks from the diff instead of staging all the changes made in a file. If git is not able to split the hunk the way you want there is the &lt;code&gt;e&lt;/code&gt; option you can give to manually create a hunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;submodules&#34;&gt;Submodules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is useful when you want to nest a git repo inside another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;github-actions&#34;&gt;Github Actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allows you to have workflows attached to your git push commands.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Software I Use</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/software_i_use/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 12:19:50 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/software_i_use/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;I use Linux as my primary operating system. The flavour of Linux that I use is ArchLinux. Which is great on multiple counts. One, it follows a minimalist approach of giving you only the bare minimum packages and configurations by default. Two, it is a rolling release which means that you get the updates of all the packages you have installed, as soon as they are published. The third reason is the presence of the AUR (Arch User Repository) which enables you to install a lot of niche packages with just a single command. All the complicated stuff like the download and configuration are taken care of for you under-the-hood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not use any of the full fledged desktop environments (DE) like &lt;code&gt;Gnome&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;KDE&lt;/code&gt;. Rather  I use i3 which is just a tiling window manager. Until recently I was using Openbox which was a floating window manager. Using just a window manager means that you get to pick and choose and build your own desktop environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-desktop-environment-includes-the-following&#34;&gt;My desktop environment includes the following:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;polybar&lt;/code&gt; as my status bar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;dunst&lt;/code&gt; for my notifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;xcompmgr&lt;/code&gt; for window effects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;dmenu&lt;/code&gt; as my application switcher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;sxhkd&lt;/code&gt; for keyboard shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;common-applications-that-i-use&#34;&gt;Common Applications that I use&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Music player - &lt;code&gt;mpd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video player - &lt;code&gt;mpv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Browser - &lt;code&gt;brave&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text editor - &lt;code&gt;gvim&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notes app - &lt;code&gt;amplenote&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pdf viewer - &lt;code&gt;evince&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code editor - &lt;a href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/notes/vim_tips/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Terminal emulator - &lt;code&gt;xfce4-terminal&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Image viewer - &lt;code&gt;sxiv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graphical file manager - &lt;code&gt;pcmanfm-qt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;research-related-applications&#34;&gt;Research related applications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Academic document preparation - LaTeX(&lt;code&gt;texlive&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reference management - &lt;code&gt;zotero&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;special-purpose-applications&#34;&gt;Special-purpose applications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bookmark management - &lt;code&gt;buku&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Terminal file-manager - &lt;code&gt;lf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Terminal image preview - &lt;code&gt;ueberzug&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calendar management - &lt;code&gt;khal&lt;/code&gt; , &lt;code&gt;vdirsyncer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;low-level-configurations&#34;&gt;Low-level configurations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;zsh&lt;/code&gt; as my shell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;btrfs&lt;/code&gt; as my filesystem format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;uefi&lt;/code&gt; comptabile bootloader&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Understanding diff</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/notes/understanding_diff/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 11:45:39 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/notes/understanding_diff/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Q. Do you find it difficult at times to interpret the output of &lt;code&gt;diff foo bar&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. The output shows what changes you need to make to &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt; in order to make it identical to &lt;code&gt;bar&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Lifehacks for a Workaholic</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/lifehacks/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 12:41:17 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/selected/lifehacks/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Life is mostly a game of achieving the best of both worlds (or many worlds).
Here are some of my recommendations for someone who wants to run multiple tasks at a time but also seeks perfection in all that they do.
There is something called the Getting Things Done (GTD) methodology as made famous by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Getting-Things-Done/dp/0143573195&#34;&gt;David Allen&lt;/a&gt; in his book of the same name. If you find the book a bit dry, watch videos by people on youtube like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@aliabdaal&#34;&gt;Ali Abdaal&lt;/a&gt;. Two other interesting books to read are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40121378-atomic-habits&#34;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt; by James Clear and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25744928-deep-work&#34;&gt;Deep Work&lt;/a&gt; by Cal Newport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-amplenote&#34;&gt;Use Amplenote&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amplenote is an app that goes hand in hand with the GTD methodology.
Before coming to Amplenote my workflow involved seperate apps for journalling (Obsidian or Logseq), task-management (Trello or Taskwarrior) and calendar (google calendar).
Amplenote is designed to do all these at the same time and it also has a mobile app that is easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-technique-in-brief&#34;&gt;The technique in brief&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identify the most important projects that you need to work on based on your values and goals in life.
Keep in mind that what competes with your goals are often, your other goals.
For collaborative projects if you have regular group meetings, create a meeting minutes document where you log the important points that were discussed. Create a condensed version of this in your notes. Turn any actionable item to a task.
Use the calendar blocking technique to block it on your calendar.
Keep a work log for each project where you document the progress you made each day and your thoughts on it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Toolkit for a Machine Learning Researcher</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/toolkit/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 10:34:25 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/selected/toolkit/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;When you start out by doing computer vision problems in Deep Learning, you quickly run into the issue of having to deal with remote machines. Especially one&amp;rsquo;s that have GPU designed for such tasks. When you have to deal with these headless machines that do not have a display or user interface, there is a need to learn a plethora of command line tools that are available on linux.
In order to learn more about the tools that are mentioned below you can watch these set of lectures by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z56Jmr9Z34Q&amp;amp;list=PLyzOVJj3bHQuloKGG59rS43e29ro7I57J&#34;&gt;Missing Semester&lt;/a&gt; or follow &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@LukeSmithxyz&#34;&gt;Luke Smith&lt;/a&gt; on youtube. Some of these tools have a big learning curve. Which is the price you pay in order to reap the rewards in the long term. However if you are someone who just wants to get things done and move along or are short of time. I will give alternate suggestions wherever applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tools-that-are-useful-for-anyone&#34;&gt;Tools That are Useful for Anyone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ssh&#34;&gt;SSH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the very first ones would be &lt;strong&gt;SSH&lt;/strong&gt; which helps you to login to a remote machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;vim&#34;&gt;ViM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very next need is a text editor that can run entirely in your terminal without needing a UI. On Linux, you can choose from ViM, Nano, emacs or mcedit. Oh, if you are one of those persons who can never let go of the jupyter-notebook IDE. And would prefer running code on the remote machine using jupyter-notebooks, I would recommend you watch this video &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7jiPeIFXb6U&#34;&gt;I dont like notebooks&lt;/a&gt; by AllenAI researcher Joel Grus. If you are short on time you can instead explore the VSCode IDE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;git&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git is the modern code version control software. It is one of Linus Torvalds contributions to open source that he believes has an even greater impact than the Linux kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;screen-or-tmux&#34;&gt;Screen or Tmux&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code for deep learning takes hours or even days to run. Although the remote server can remain switched on all the time, you do not want your laptop switched on all the time. When you disconnect your ssh connection or close the current terminal, you kill all associated programs that are running. How do you keep them running even when you close your terminal and log out of the client machine (your laptop)? Using programs like &lt;code&gt;screen&lt;/code&gt; or its modern variant &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conda&#34;&gt;Conda&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conda can be installed through either of the distributions Anaconda or Miniconda. Conda might be frustrating at time with the time taken to install packages. Use conda to install mamba and then use mamba in place of conda for all package installations. There are times when you might have to use pip. For example when the package is not there in conda. Or you need to install a package directly from it&amp;rsquo;s git version. But in all other cases you are much better off using conda for environment management because it can version control non Python software as well. You often require non Python software for compiling python packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;research-reading--writing&#34;&gt;Research Reading &amp;amp; Writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use markdown files for quick documentation. There are note editors that can read and render markdown like Obsidian, Logseq, Notion etc. Even ViM has some basic support for markdown. Use LaTeX for academic document preparation. Use Zotero for storing, annotating research papers and exporting the references as a bib file for use in LaTeX citations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;machine-learning-specific-tools&#34;&gt;Machine Learning Specific Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tensorflow-of-pytorch&#34;&gt;Tensorflow of PyTorch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both are great frameworks that are being actively developed. One pitfall that I have fallen into is thinking that the framework that makes it easy to write code is the best. This might not always be the case. Maybe it is good for the engineer who is playing with ready made stuff but not so good for the researcher who needs to look into the internals of the code they are running. PyTorch might be a tad better for the beginner than tensorflow in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wandb&#34;&gt;Wandb&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to capture the learning process is important to troubleshoot problems with the learning. You can visualize the training loss in each iteration of your epoch and monitor the validation loss after every epoch. You can also look into how the weights are changing. Or you could use model attribution techniques to create heatmaps etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>About this webpage</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/posts/website/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 20:47:07 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/posts/website/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;github-actions&#34;&gt;Github Actions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A website is basically an HTML file on someone else&amp;rsquo;s computer. Once you have this, then you need to have a unique easy-to-remember address to type into the address bar of your browser. This is translated into an IP address by your browser by looking up the number on the yellow pages of the internet, a process which is also called Domain Name Resolution and for which there are dedicated servers known as DNS servers.
Therefore to run a website the minimum you require is a computer and a domain name. Luckily Github provides both to you for free. A computer through &lt;strong&gt;Github Actions&lt;/strong&gt; and a free domain name that includes .github.io.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;hugo-a-static-site-generator&#34;&gt;Hugo, A static-site generator&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown is a text formatting language invented by none other than the legendary Aaron Swartz. Instead of directly writing in html, you get to write in markdown and have software convert it into html.
&lt;strong&gt;Hugo&lt;/strong&gt; is software that does this among other things. CSS is a language that was invented to stylize the content of your website.
Hugo also generates CSS files that does the beautification of your website.
It is also called a static site generator. Create a repository in github that ends with .github.io and clone it in your machine.
Copy the contents of the public folder generated by hugo to this git repo.
When you set up github actions, Github has a computer that serves the content of this repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;theme&#34;&gt;Theme&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme is inspired from &lt;a href=&#34;https://lukesmith.xyz/&#34;&gt;Luke Smith&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Machine Learning Resources</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/books/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 19:28:06 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/selected/books/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;These are books I have read (at least partly) and know to be good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Learning-Python-Second-Fran%C3%A7ois-Chollet/dp/1617296864/&#34;&gt;Deep Learning with Python&lt;/a&gt; by Francois Chollet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pyimagesearch.com/deep-learning-computer-vision-python-book/&#34;&gt;Deep Learning for Computer Vision&lt;/a&gt; by Adrian Rosebrock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Machine-Learning-Algorithmic-Perspective-Recognition/dp/1466583282/&#34;&gt;Machine Learning: An Algorithmic Perspective&lt;/a&gt; by Stephen Marsland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Statistics-Mining-Machine-Learning-Astronomy/dp/0691198306&#34;&gt;Statistics, Data Mining, and Machine Learning in Astronomy&lt;/a&gt; by Željko Ivezić, Andrew J. Connolly , Jacob T. VanderPlas &amp;amp; Alexander Gray&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Deep-Learning-Adaptive-Computation-Machine/dp/0262035618&#34;&gt;Deep Learning &lt;/a&gt; by Ian Goodfellow , Yoshua Bengio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Pattern-Recognition-Learning-Information-Statistics/dp/0387310738/&#34;&gt;Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; by Christopher M. Bishop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are books I believe are great and which I would like to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Information-Theory-Inference-Learning-Algorithms/dp/0521642981&#34;&gt;Information Theory, Inference and Learning Algorithms&lt;/a&gt; by David J. C. MacKay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-Statistical-Learning-Applications-Statistics/dp/3031387465/&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Statistical Learning&lt;/a&gt; by Gareth James, Daniela Witten, Trevor Hastie, Robert Tibshirani &amp;amp; Jonathan Taylor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non-book recommendations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Videos by Grant Sanderson from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@3blue1brown&#34;&gt;3Blue1Brown&lt;/a&gt; channel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://karpathy.github.io/&#34;&gt;Andrej Karpathy&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title></title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/grwidget/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/grwidget/</guid>
		<description>      &lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34; media=&#34;screen&#34;&gt;
        .gr_grid_container {
          /* customize grid container div here. eg: width: 500px; */
        }

        .gr_grid_book_container {
          /* customize book cover container div here */
          float: left;
          width: 98px;
          height: 160px;
          padding: 0px 0px;
          overflow: hidden;
        }
      &lt;/style&gt;
      &lt;div id=&#34;gr_grid_widget_1719130852&#34;&gt;
        &lt;!-- Show static html as a placeholder in case js is not enabled - javascript include will override this if things work --&gt;
            &lt;h2&gt;
      &lt;a style=&#34;text-decoration: none;&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/5186783-linn?shelf=read&amp;utm_medium=api&amp;utm_source=grid_widget&#34;&gt;Linn&#39;s bookshelf: read&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h2&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Operation Thunderbolt: Flight 139 and the Raid on Entebbe Airport, the Most Audacious Hostage Rescue Mission in History&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25318813-operation-thunderbolt&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Operation Thunderbolt: Flight 139 and the Raid on Entebbe Airport, the Most Audacious Hostage Rescue Mission in History&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1433450810l/25318813._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;ഖസാക്കിന്റെ ഇതിഹാസം | Khasakkinte Ithihasam | The Legends of Khasak&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2623267-khasakkinte-ithihasam-the-legends-of-khasak&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ഖസാക്കിന്റെ ഇതിഹാസം | Khasakkinte Ithihasam | The Legends of Khasak&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1462709894l/2623267._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Kafka on the Shore&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/4929.Kafka_on_the_Shore&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Kafka on the Shore&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1429638085l/4929._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The Tell-Tale Brain: A Neuroscientist&#39;s Quest for What Makes Us Human&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8574712-the-tell-tale-brain&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Tell-Tale Brain: A Neuroscientist&#39;s Quest for What Makes Us Human&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348750093l/8574712._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Introducing Psychology: A Graphic Guide&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26862950-introducing-psychology&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Introducing Psychology: A Graphic Guide&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1443955316l/26862950._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;ആൽഫ | Alpha&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17910389-alpha&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ആൽഫ | Alpha&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1471277750l/17910389._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23692271-sapiens&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1703329310l/23692271._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Rich Dad Poor Dad: What the Rich Teach Their Kids About Money That the Poor and Middle Class Do Not!&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/39924789-rich-dad-poor-dad&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Rich Dad Poor Dad: What the Rich Teach Their Kids About Money That the Poor and Middle Class Do Not!&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1524451661l/39924789._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The Naked Woman: A Study of the Female Body&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/124663.The_Naked_Woman&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Naked Woman: A Study of the Female Body&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1316727767l/124663._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Eat, Drink, and Be Healthy: The Harvard Medical School Guide to Healthy Eating&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34466919-eat-drink-and-be-healthy&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Eat, Drink, and Be Healthy: The Harvard Medical School Guide to Healthy Eating&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1505658899l/34466919._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25744928-deep-work&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1447957962l/25744928._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Atomic Habits: An Easy &amp; Proven Way to Build Good Habits &amp; Break Bad Ones&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40121378-atomic-habits&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Atomic Habits: An Easy &amp; Proven Way to Build Good Habits &amp; Break Bad Ones&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1655988385l/40121378._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;In Order to Live: A North Korean Girl&#39;s Journey to Freedom&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26063290-in-order-to-live&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;In Order to Live: A North Korean Girl&#39;s Journey to Freedom&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1439054113l/26063290._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The Tales of Beedle the Bard (Hogwarts Library, #3)&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3950967-the-tales-of-beedle-the-bard&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Tales of Beedle the Bard&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1630876355l/3950967._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Man’s Search for Meaning&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/4069.Man_s_Search_for_Meaning&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Man’s Search for Meaning&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1535419394l/4069._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Food Rules: An Eater&#39;s Manual&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7015635-food-rules&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Food Rules: An Eater&#39;s Manual&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348526224l/7015635._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Toxic Parents: Overcoming Their Hurtful Legacy and Reclaiming Your Life&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/103999.Toxic_Parents&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Toxic Parents: Overcoming Their Hurtful Legacy and Reclaiming Your Life&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1320537700l/103999._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;മനുഷ്യരറിയാൻ | Manushyanariyan&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/49994675-manushyanariyan&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;മനുഷ്യരറിയാൻ | Manushyanariyan&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1576505592l/49994675._SX98_SY160_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Free Will&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13180629-free-will&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Free Will&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1332924961l/13180629._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Top 10 for Men&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6090934-top-10-for-men&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Top 10 for Men&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348802536l/6090934._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;br style=&#34;clear: both&#34;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;gr_grid_branding&#34; style=&#34;font-size: .9em; color: #382110; text-decoration: none; float: right; clear: both&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/5186783-linn&#34;&gt;Linn&#39;s favorite books »&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;noscript&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Share &lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/&#34;&gt;book reviews&lt;/a&gt; and ratings with Linn, and even join a &lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/group&#34;&gt;book club&lt;/a&gt; on Goodreads.&lt;/noscript&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;script src=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/grid_widget/5186783.Linn&#39;s%20bookshelf:%20read?cover_size=medium&amp;hide_link=&amp;hide_title=&amp;num_books=30&amp;order=d&amp;shelf=read&amp;sort=date_read&amp;widget_id=1719130852&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>About Me</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/about/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/about/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;I am Linn Abraham. I am basically a computer nerd, who also happens to be very passionate about Science.
I am doing a Ph.D.  where I work on solving problems in Astrophysics using Machine Learning.
A few of the problems that I work on are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated galaxy morphology classification using Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prediction of solar flares from Active Region images using Deep Learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detection of HI sources from radio data cubes using 3D CNNs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work on the prediction of solar flares using Deep Learning is part of a JRF Project funded by ISRO. I developed and currently maintain the website for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://suit.iucaa.in&#34;&gt;Solar Ultraviolet Imaging Telescope (SUIT)&lt;/a&gt; along with my teammates in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/The+Inter-University+Centre+for+Astronomy+and+Astrophysics/@18.5592415,73.8253115,3a,75y,90t/data=!3m8!1e2!3m6!1sAF1QipP8MobfPKzfBxsux1HhY-jz_zNzlL24z6G5CHuB!2e10!3e12!6shttps:%2F%2Flh5.googleusercontent.com%2Fp%2FAF1QipP8MobfPKzfBxsux1HhY-jz_zNzlL24z6G5CHuB%3Dw114-h86-k-no!7i4000!8i3000!4m11!1m2!2m1!1sIUCAA!3m7!1s0x3bc2bf45db40022d:0x1efcdd94c3239f51!8m2!3d18.5592415!4d73.8253115!10e5!15sCgVJVUNBQZIBEnJlc2VhcmNoX2luc3RpdHV0ZeABAA!16zL20vMDQ0ODg1?entry=ttu&#34;&gt;IUCAA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://machinelearningmaniac.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; which is a collection of random articles that I write in relation to machine learning and astronomy. This is my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/linnabraham&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; page. You can also connect with me on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/linn-abraham/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the movies I watched recently &lt;a href=&#34;https://trakt.tv/users/linnabraham&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Here are some of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/grwidget/&#34;&gt;books&lt;/a&gt; that I have read and enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Quick Links</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/links/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/links/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Hey cool&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	</channel>
</rss>
