<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
	<title>Linn Abraham&#39;s homepage</title>
	<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/</link>
	<description>Recent content in Selecteds on Linn Abraham&#39;s homepage</description>
	<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
	<language>en-us</language>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 09:42:07 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://linnabraham.me/selected/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	
	
	<item>
		<title>How do we know the Sun&#39;s temperature?</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/posts/sun_temperature/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 18:00:45 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/posts/sun_temperature/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is often humbling to think how far humanity has reached in its
efforts to understand the cosmos. Using the systematic knowledge
building methodology that we call Science, we humans have been able to
find distances to the Sun, moon and planets. Weigh the Earth while
living on just a tiny sliver of its surface called the crust. Weigh the
Sun and find the temperature and pressure in it&amp;rsquo;s interior. Most of this
was done before the time of rockets and satellites with just pen, paper
and the equations of science. In this article let us retrace the path
that has been taken by several great thinkers and scientists who
contributed to the repository of knowledge that we have today. The
primary question we want to address is how hot is the Sun? We have seen
iron rods glowing red and white when heated. If so, then how much more
hot must the Sun be ? What is the temperature on its surface as well as
in it&amp;rsquo;s core?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-far-away-is-the-sun&#34;&gt;How far away is the Sun?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Kepler&amp;rsquo;s third law of planetary motion, we know that
&lt;/p&gt;
$$T^2 \propto a^3$$
&lt;p&gt; Where T is the orbital period of a planet around the
Sun and a is the semi-major axis of the orbit. By taking ratios one can
convert this to an equation.
&lt;/p&gt;
$$\frac{T_1^2}{T_2^2} = \frac{a_1^3}{a_2^3}$$
&lt;p&gt; Now let us put Earth as
the second planet and Venus as the first planet. We define the Earth&amp;rsquo;s
orbital period around the Sun as one year and its semi-major axis as one
astronomical unit (AU). This allows us to calculate the distance from
Venus to Sun in terms of AU if we know the orbital time period of Venus.
&lt;/p&gt;
$$T_1^2 = a_1^3$$
&lt;p&gt; For the purposes of this discussion, let me call the
semi-major axis length itself as the distance. Since the orbital period
of Venus can be found by observations, we can find the distance between
Venus and Sun in terms of AU. One minus this distance would then give
the distance between Earth and Venus in terms of AU. Now consider what
happens during the Venus transit, that is, when the Venus comes directly
between the Sun and Earth. If at this time, we measure the actual
distance from Earth to Venus, we can find out the length of one AU. Such
a distance measurement can be done using the parallax method. Doing all
the calculations we arrive at an answer of 150 million kilometers for
the length of one AU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-big-is-the-earth&#34;&gt;How big is the Earth?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best arguments for the round-earther&amp;rsquo;s claim of a spherical
Earth is that the shape of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s shadow on the moon is circular
during any lunar eclipse. During a lunar eclipse, the Sun illuminates
the Earth from behind and its shadow fals on the moon. Regardless of
when or where this happens, the shadow is always circular and a sphere
is the only shape that fits such a scenario. This fact was known during
the time of Erastothenes, who lived a very long time ago and which is
evident from the name alone. We know that the Sun is so far away that
the light rays coming from it are parallel. Erastothenes also assumed
this to be true and went about calculating the Earth&amp;rsquo;s radius based on
this assumption. He found out that at the same time when the Sun is
directly overhead at Syene in Egypt, the Sun cast a shadow that is 7
degrees inclined from the vertical at Alexandria. By knowing the actual
distance from Syene to Alexandria and the angular distance of 7 degrees,
the circumference of the Earth can be calculated. The final answer is
6371 km.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-we-know-the-suns-mass&#34;&gt;How do we know the Sun&amp;rsquo;s mass?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henry Cavendish (1731-1810) is the man credited with weighing the Earth
for the first time. He did this by measuring the gravitation constant
that appears in Newton&amp;rsquo;s Law of Universal Gravitation. He was able to do
this because the radius of the Earth was already known by that time.
Knowing the Earth&amp;rsquo;s mass makes us one step closer to finding the mass of
the Sun. We know that the Earth goes around the Sun in a sort of
circular motion. The centripetal acceleration is provided by the force
of the Sun&amp;rsquo;s gravitational attraction on the Earth. The centripetal
acceleration in uniform circular motin is given by \(\frac{v^2}{r}\).
Where v is the speed of Earth&amp;rsquo;s motion around the Sun. The speed of
Earth&amp;rsquo;s motion around Sun is trivial to find once we know the
circumference of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s orbit. We divide that quantity by the time
taken for one full revolution which is one year. By equating this to the
force of gravitation between Sun and Earth, we can find out the mass of
the Sun since we already know the mass of the Earth and the Sun-Earth
distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-blackbody-temperature-of-the-sun&#34;&gt;The blackbody temperature of the Sun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A blackbody temperature or effective temperature of an object is the
surface temperature that the object would have if it were a perfect
blackbody. This effective temperature can be found if one knows the
luminosity of the blackbody and its surface area, using the
Steffan-Boltzmann law. The luminosity is defined as the total power
radiated by the object. A related term, apparent brightness or received
energy flux, is the power per unit surface area of the detector. This
can be computed by diving the total power incident on your detector by
the total surface area of your detector which would depend on your
aperture size etc. This apparent brightness is affected by the true
luminosity of the object as well as the distance to the object. For an
isotropically radiating object this relationship can be expressed as,
&lt;/p&gt;
$$\textrm{Apparent brightness} = \frac{L}{4\pi d^2}$$
&lt;p&gt; Where L is the
luminosity, and d is the distance to the object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To calculate the effective temperature for the Sun, we need to know its
linear size, that is the Sun&amp;rsquo;s diameter. Since the distance to the Sun
is already known, by knowing the angular size of the Sun, i.e. the angle
subtended by the Sun on the sky, we can compute its linear size. Since
the Sun is very far away, the angles involved are quite small so that we
can use the small-angle approximation to find this. Doing all this we
get the Sun&amp;rsquo;s effective surface temperature to be 5,800 K.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-suns-core-temperature&#34;&gt;The Sun&amp;rsquo;s core temperature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By knowing the Sun&amp;rsquo;s mass and volume we can estimate the pressure in the
Sun. By doing the calculations we find that the pressure is so high that
matter can only exist in the plasma state. That is, atoms are stripped
of all its electrons. Such a plasma is however electrically neutral on
the whole and the inter-particle distances are sufficient for it to have
a perfect gas behaviour. This allows us to estimate the temperature of
the plasma from the perfect gas law provided we first find out the
pressure at the core. The perfect gas law states that \(P = nkT\), where P
is the pressure of the gas, n is the number density of particles and T
is the temperature. Using the law we find the temperature at the Sun&amp;rsquo;s
core to be \(1.5 \times 10^7\) K or 15 million degrees Kelvin.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Programming: Tools and Resources</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/programming_tools/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 09:42:07 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/selected/programming_tools/</guid>
		<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://colab.research.google.com/&#34;&gt;Google Colab&lt;/a&gt; - A free Linux computer to practice coding, through a jupyter notebook IDE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://exercism.org/&#34;&gt;Exercism&lt;/a&gt; - Problems to practice your coding skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://replit.com/learn&#34;&gt;Replit&lt;/a&gt; - Platform to learn and teach programming with help of virtual machines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/&#34;&gt;Kaggle&lt;/a&gt; - Cloud based jupyter notebook and datasets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Astronomy: Academic Resources</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/astronomy_books/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 09:20:25 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/selected/astronomy_books/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Books I have found helpful in learning astronomy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Astrophysics-Physicists-Arnab-Rai-Choudhuri/dp/0521815533/&#34;&gt;Astrophysics for Physicists&lt;/a&gt; by Arnab Rai Choudhuri&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.in/INTRODUCTION-ASTROPHYSICS-2-ED/dp/812034071X/&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Astrophysics&lt;/a&gt; by Baidyanath Basu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Fundamental-Astronomy-Hannu-Karttunen/dp/3662530449/&#34;&gt;Fundamental Astronomy&lt;/a&gt; by  Hannu Karttunen, Pekka Kröger, Heikki Oja, Markku Poutanen &amp;amp; Karl Johan Donner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/linnabraham/astropython/blob/master/aavsoguide.pdf&#34;&gt;Hands-On Astrophysics&lt;/a&gt; by the AAVSO team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://radiojove.gsfc.nasa.gov/education/educationalcd/RadioAstronomyTutorial/Workbook%20PDF%20Files/Introduction.pdf&#34;&gt;Basics of Radio Astronomy&lt;/a&gt; by the JPL team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Physical-Universe-Introduction-Astronomy-Books/dp/0935702059/&#34;&gt;The Physical Universe: An Introduction to Astronomy&lt;/a&gt; by Frank H. Shu&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.in/gp/product/0199674752/&#34;&gt;Nature&amp;rsquo;s Third Cycle: A Story of Sunspots&lt;/a&gt; by Arnab Rai Choudhuri&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://openstax.org/details/books/astronomy-2e/&#34;&gt;Astronomy&lt;/a&gt; by Fraknoi, A., Morrison, D., &amp;amp; Wolff, S. C.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are books I believe are great and which I would like to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-Modern-Astrophysics-Bradley-Carroll/dp/1108422160/&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Modern Astrophysics&lt;/a&gt; by Bradley W. Carroll &amp;amp;  Dale A. Ostlie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Understanding-Variable-Stars-John-Percy/dp/1107403707&#34;&gt;Understanding Variable Stars&lt;/a&gt; by John R. Percy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Exploring-X-ray-Universe-Frederick-Seward/dp/0521884837/&#34;&gt;Exploring the X-ray Universe&lt;/a&gt; by Frederick D. Seward &amp;amp; Philip A. Charles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Radiative-Processes-Astrophysics-Lightman-Rybicki/dp/B0095H96U4/&#34;&gt;Radiative Processes in Astrophysics&lt;/a&gt; by Alan P. Rybicki, George B. &amp;amp; Lightman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Maximum likelihood versus Bayesian</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/posts/maximum_likelihood/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2024 12:39:45 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/posts/maximum_likelihood/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Given that you observed a set of data points \(\mathbf{x_{1}}\),&amp;hellip;,\(\mathbf{x_{N}}\), can you produce the probability distribution function from which it was sampled?
This problem is known as &lt;em&gt;density estimation&lt;/em&gt; and is related to the problem of model selection, one of the central problems in pattern recognition.
However, it is to be considered if this is a sensible question to ask. Since any probability distribution that is non-zero at each of the sampled data points, is a possible candidate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parametric distributions are a subset of probability distributions which can be completely defined by a small set of parameters.
For example, Gaussian distributions are defined by their mean and variance.
So for the sake of simplicity, let us assume that the nature of the sampled probability distribution is Gaussian.
The Gaussian distribution is defined by,
&lt;/p&gt;
$$ N(x|\mu, \sigma^{2}) = \frac{1}{(2\pi\sigma^{2})^{1/2}} \exp{\{-\frac{1}{2\sigma^2}(x-\mu)^{2}\}} $$
&lt;p&gt;
Then our goal reduces to estimating the model parameters \(\mu\) and \(\sigma\).
The joint probability of two independent events is given by the product of the marginal probabilities for each event separately.
Since the samples are always assumed to be independently and identically distributed (iid),
the probability of observing the data given, the mean \(\mu\) and variance \(\sigma^{2}\).&lt;/p&gt;
$$ p(\mathbf{x}|\mu,\sigma^{2}) = \Pi_{n=1}^{N} N(x_n|\mu, \sigma^{2}) $$
&lt;p&gt;
This is called the likelihood function, considered as a function of \(\mu\) and \(\sigma^{2}\).
That is, the likelihood of observing the data, given the model parameters.
Once we have such a function of the model parameters, it is straight forward to maximize it and estimate the parameters.
In practice, we always maximize the log of this function.
Since the log is a monotically increasing function, maximizing the log achieves the same as maximizing the original function.
This, apart from simplifying the mathematical analysis, helps with numerical precision of computer which is prone to underflow when dealing with the product of very small numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might seem strange that one is asked to maximize the data given the parameters, instead of maximizing the parameters, given the data.
Anyhow, doing the analysis, one finds that the maximum likelihood estimate of the mean is given by,
&lt;/p&gt;
$$ \mu_{ML} = \frac{1}{N} \Sigma_{n=1}^{N}x_{n} $$
&lt;p&gt;
Which is effectively the sample mean.
Similarly, the maximum likelihood estimate of the variance turns out to be the sample variance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can apply the same&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Probabilities in Machine Learning</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/posts/probabilities_in_ml/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2024 10:07:20 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/posts/probabilities_in_ml/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of probability becomes more complicated the further you try to understand it.  There is no one answer to the question - What is meant by &amp;ldquo;probability&amp;rdquo;. There are in fact entire schools of thoughts when it comes to the interpretation of what are probabilities and how to use them. Two of the more popular ones are known as &lt;code&gt;Frequentism&#39; and &lt;/code&gt;Bayesianism&amp;rsquo;. Christopher Bishop in his highly acclaimed textbook on Machine Learning, mentions probability theory, decision theory and information theory as three important tools when it comes to learning machine learning. This article motivates the need to pursue probability in machine learning by first listing some areas where you encounter the concept. Then it tries to give an overview of the difficulties in understanding probabilities by listing some of the different interpretation of probabilities. Afterwards it introduces two concepts that are crucial to understanding probabilities - the concept of a probability distribution function and Bayes theorem which is one of the most important concepts in probability theory. The last two discussions are heavily inspired from the youtube videos by 3Blue1Brown&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;use-in-machine-learning&#34;&gt;Use in Machine Learning&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Randomness and probabilistic methods come up a lot in machine learning.  Here are a few of the more common ones. There are learning algorithms that make use of randomness and probability concepts such as the Random Forest, the Naive Bayes Classifier or even Bayesian Neural Networks. Genetic algorithms are optimization algorithms inspired by randomness and natural selection. Gaussian processes are a type of probabilistic model used for regression and classification tasks. Bootstrapping is a resampling technique used in ensemble methods like bagging. Expectation Maximization or EM is an optimization algorithm used in unsupervised learning especially in clustering and Gaussian Mixture Models (GMM). Dropout is a common regularization technique used in neural networks that drops random neurons during the training process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Randomness is also important during the training process for initialization of model weights, train-test splitting of datasets, used in optimization methods such as stochastic gradient descent and even in random search during hyper-parameter tuning. Often in ML, we try to interpret the outputs of activation functions etc. as probabilities. A related aspect is how we design or interpret the common evaluation metrics that comes up in discriminant models like sensitivity, specificity etc. This is one area where we need to use concepts from probability such as Bayes theorem for properly understanding the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;physical-and-evidential-probabilities&#34;&gt;Physical and Evidential Probabilities&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two ways in which probabilities are used, which may be called physical (objective or frequency) and evidential (Bayesian) probabilities. Physical probabilities are associated with physical systems that are considered random in nature such as rolling dice or radioactive decay. There are events associated with such systems that happen at a fixed rate or relative frequency. Physical probabilities are invoked to explain such stable frequencies. This is the kind of probability that most people are introduced to during their primary education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other kind of probability, evidential probability, can be considered as a degree of belief in a statement as supported by available evidence. It can be associated to any statement, even one without any kind of randomness involved. This is a kind of probability that is used very informally in daily life but has more importance in academia and research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;interpretations-of-probabilities&#34;&gt;Interpretations of Probabilities&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following are the four main interpretations of probabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical Interpretation (A priori) - This interpretation is attributed to Pierre-Simon Laplace who assumed by what has been called the ``principle of insufficient reason&amp;quot;, that all possible outcomes of an event are equally likely if there are no reasons to assume otherwise. Probability of an event is then the ratio of number of outcomes favourable to the event to the total number of outcomes possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empirical Interpretation (A posteriori) - This interpretation is sometimes called Frequentist. However the term is also used to refer to ``physical probability&amp;quot; as a whole when contrasting it with Bayesian probabilities. According to this, the probability of an event is the relative frequency of occurence after repeating the process for a large number of times under similar conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subjective Interpretation - As mentioned above probabilities can be used as a measure of the degree of belief of an individual who is assessing the uncertainty of a situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Axiomatic Interpretation - The mathematics of probability can be developed on an entirely axiomatic basis that is independent of any interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;interpreting-probability-density-functions-pdf&#34;&gt;Interpreting Probability Density Functions (PDF)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probability density functions are ubiquitous in statistics and probability theory. To motivate the need for such a function we need to shift our thinking from a discrete context to a continuous context. When you consider experiments such as tossing a coin or rolling a dice etc. the outcomes you are interested in are often discrete. Like for e.g., the probability of getting two heads when a coin is tossed 5 times. However one can imagine a case where the outcomes can take any value in a continuous range. In such a case no matter how small a value you assign to each of these outcomes, you would run into the following problem. The sum of all these probabilities would add upto infinity. This means that in such a scenario, it no longer makes sense to talk about probabilities of individual values. However if we consider a histogram where the height of the bins represents - the probability that the outcome is within a range specified by the bin widths, then we no longer have a problem. It is the area of each bin that gives the probability associated with that range. When you have bins of smaller and smaller widths you have a more refined knowledge of the probabilities in each individual bin. And you also end up with a smooth curve. But what is the height of this curve that we have ended up with? Since the width of a bin times the height is a probability, the quantity in the y-axis would have a dimension of probability over length. Hence what he have can be called a probability density. Since the probabilities are represented by areas of the individual rectangles, the total area under the curve adds upto 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When trying to interpret the probability distribution function as mentioned you might run into another problem. The probability of getting an exact value, which is the area of a very thin slice becomes zero by definition. To understand what is happening here, note that, if in the discrete case the probability of the outcome falling in one out of a collection of values was just the sum of the individual probabilities.  In the continuous case, the probability of your outcome taking a range of values is no longer the sum of individual probabilities. Instead the probabilities associated with the ranges themselves are the fundamental primitive objects we are dealing with here. In order to make more sense of this you might have to learn a bit of measure theory a branch of mathematics which provides the foundational framework for the rigorous mathematical development of probability theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bayes-theorem&#34;&gt;Bayes Theorem&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-to-use-bayes-theorem&#34;&gt;When to use Bayes theorem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important formulas in probability theory is the Bayes formula. The code idea behind the base theorem is that &amp;ldquo;Evidence should not determine beliefs but update them&amp;rdquo;. Before we try to understand what the formula is telling us let us see when it would be useful to actually apply the formula. Suppose you are shown the following description of a person called Steve. &lt;code&gt;Steve is very shy and withdrawn, invariably helpful but with very little interest in people or in the world of reality. A meek and tidy soul, he has a need for order and structure, and a passion for detail. If you are then asked the following question, &lt;/code&gt;Which of the following do you think more likely: &amp;ldquo;Steve is a librarian&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Steve is a farmer&amp;rdquo; ?  Which one might you choose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example is part of a study conducted by Psychologists David Kahneman and Amos Tversky. Their study showed that most people go with the option of Steve being a librarian. Although it is true that these traits align with the stereotypical view of a librarian than a farmer, the authors of the study show that it is irrational to come to that judgement. Their point was that almost no one thought of using the information about the ratio of farmers to librarians in their judgements. The question is not whether the partcipants had information about those statistics but whether they thought about estimating it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-use-bayes-theorem&#34;&gt;How to use Bayes theorem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say you did estimate the ratio of farmers to librarians and came up with the number 20:1.  So let us start with a sample size of 210 people. Of which there are 200 farmers and 10 librarians. Next you think about all the librarians you know and come to the estimate that 40 percent of all librarians fit the description and 10 percent of all farmers fit the same description. That is you are still saying that a librarian is 4 times more likely to fit the description than a farmer. However if you now try to find out the probability that a random person who fits the description is a librarian. It is given by,&lt;/p&gt;
$$\frac{\textrm{ 4 Librarians who fit the description}}{\textrm{ 4 Librarians + 20 Farmers who fit the description}}$$
&lt;p&gt;Which is only 16 percent. Whereas the probability that the random person would be a farmer would be 84 percent. The key takeaway here is that new evidence should not determine your beliefs in a vaccuum; it should update prior beliefs.  So the way to understand such problem is start to with all possibilities (210). Then seeing evidence restricts the space of possibilities ( 4 + 20).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;motivating-the-bayes-formula&#34;&gt;Motivating the Bayes formula&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can we generalize from this example to reach a formula? The general scenarios is the following. You have some hypothesis (or model) like the hypothesis that &lt;code&gt;Steve is a Librarian&amp;quot; or &lt;/code&gt;The coin is fair&amp;quot;. You have some evidence (data or observation) like the description about Steve that you obtained. You are mostly interested in knowing the probability that your hypothesis is true given the evidence. This is what you computed quite easily in the example above. The probability that ``Steve is a Librarian&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; given the description about Steve which we can now denote \(P (H|E) \).
w
How did we arrive at the numerator which was 4? By first calculating the  probability that the hypothesis holds without considering any of the evidence. This is called the prior and denoted \(P(H)\).
In our case we calculated the prior by taking the ratio of all librarians to farmers which came to be \(1/21\). After that we used the proportion of librarians that fit the description. This is the probability of seeing the evidence given the hypothesis is true. That is, if it is given that Steve is a librarian, we then limit our space of possibilities to the space of all librarians and ask how likely it is for a random librarian to have this description.
This is also called the likelihood and in our case it was \(4/10\).  Now by multiplying the total number of people times the prior times the likelihood we obtain the numerator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the denominator we again have the same term. But also an additional term which contains the likelihood of observing the evidence if the hypothesis is not true, which in our case was \(1/10\). Along with this we need to multiply the the prior corresponding to the case where our hypothesis is not true and the total number of people. So finally putting all these words into an equation we have,
&lt;/p&gt;
$$ P(H|E) = \frac{P(H)P(E|H)}{P(H)P(E|H)+P(\neg H)P(E|\neg H)}$$
&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/HZGCoVF3YvM&#34;&gt;Bayes theorem, the geometry of changing beliefs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Beginner&#39;s Guide to Machine Learning</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/posts/beginners_guide_to_ml/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2024 09:58:24 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/posts/beginners_guide_to_ml/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;This article is targeted towards people from a science (mainly astrophysics) background with very little hands-on experience in Python programming, especially tasks related to machine learning projects.  The goal is to get acquainted with the jargons of the trade and to understand where everything fits in, in the grand scheme of things. Maybe its helpful to think of this as a user&amp;rsquo;s manual for jump starting your machine learning journey. However before we move on to the implementation side of things it is better if we address two fundamental questions. One - Why use machine learning at all? What problems does it solve? Two - Why Python? If you find yourselves already convinced about these questions do skip ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-machine-learning&#34;&gt;Why machine learning?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most things that we as humans learn cannot be put into a sequence of instructions to be followed word to word by another human or even a machine. Think about how you learnt to walk, speak, identify plants, birds and animals, distinguish a familiar face from amidst a crowd of faces and so on. We know that this ability of the human brain has to do with at least two things, the data that was supplied and the the millions of neurons in the brain. So we can think of machine learning or ML as a way of harnessing this power of the human brain to solve problems without explicit instructions but with data and learning algorithms. The current goal is not as ambitious as building a replacement for our brain but building smaller brains dedicated for specific tasks.  We can increasingly find  people applying ML to niche problems in all walks of life with the help of curated data that is specific to whatever problem they might have. However remember that ML is no magic bullet that can solve any issue thrown at it. It helps us to predict patterns in data which are difficult for the average human, by delegating the effort to computers. However it fails when the problem itself has no patterns - think of why ML cannot help you to hack the share market. Also it fails when there are patterns, but the data you have is not enough to capture the variance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;machine-learning-vs-deep-learning&#34;&gt;Machine learning vs Deep learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep learning refers to a special class of machine learning techniques. Although there is no strict boundary here, there are some cues that help us distinguish between these. Most deep learning techniques make use of neural networks. Often there are layers of these networks stacked on top of each other that makes them “deep&amp;quot;. One advantage that comes with using neural  networks versus traditional learning algorithms is that they are quite versatile and do not require data to be transformed to the specific requirements of the underlying algorithm. However this is often where the algorithms lose its interpretability. Hence the coinage that neural networks are black boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cuda-and-the-gpu-revolution&#34;&gt;CUDA and The GPU revolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When PCs transformed from being mostly text based to being heavily dependent on graphics, people developed CPUs  that are specialized for matrix manipulations. Since that is what essential a computer screen is, a matrix of pixel intensity values. Such specialized CPUs are called Graphics Processing Units or GPUs. The GPU market was mostly driven by the demands of the gaming industry for high-end graphics. The real breakthrough in deep learning occurred when researchers found a use for these in training neural networks. NVIDIA one of the GPU manufacturing company opened up the use of its GPU for anyone interested in doing such things by introducing a platform called CUDA. The python deep learning libraries that we are going to get introduced to make use of the CUDA platform in order to run code on the GPUs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-python&#34;&gt;Why Python?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A programming language is fundamentally a language that helps us speak to the machine. So does it matter which language one uses or are all languages created equal? You probably guessed the answer - it does.  Each language comes with it&amp;rsquo;s own set of advantages and disadvantages. The conveniences, the learning curve, the performance etc. Let us try to understand what some of the strengths and weakness of Python are when it comes to coding machine learning algorithms. Most importantly what are the trade-offs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;software-libraries&#34;&gt;Software libraries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one makes heavy use of software libraries one saves time by not reinventing the wheel.  Python comes with a standard &amp;ldquo;library&amp;rdquo; of code that is used for implementing things widely used in the community like math functions. However when it comes to specialized uses like astronomy, machine learning etc., there are other software libraries that are available on the internet in places like PyPi, anaconda, github and the like. These external software libraries or software dependencies need to be installed using package managers like pip or conda (for the curious,  PIP is a recursive acronym for Pip Installs Packages).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disadvantage of using external software libraries is that the code is no longer in one’s control and very often subject to change.  Python itself is a  very dynamic language that keeps changing at a fast pace. As of writing this article the latest version of Python is 3.12. On top that now you need to contend with the update pace of these external libraries. In science where reproducibility is critical, how do you make sure that your code is reproducible by someone at a later point in time? This is in fact very difficult. There is no guarantee that even if you have someone&amp;rsquo;s python code you would be able to run it. This is why you often find files named requirements.txt or environment.yml etc. which is used to specify version numbers for all the external library code used in a project and that is guaranteed to work. Now the onus is on the user to install the exact versions specified in order to run the code. So far so good but if you were to run multiple scripts like this every time one would have to uninstall and reinstall specific version of external packages. This motivates the need for a Python &amp;ldquo;virtual environment&amp;rdquo;.  Pip or Conda, the Python package managers also allow us to create named virtual environments where we can have different version of same packages.  Think of virtual environments like isolated containers where different versions of the same software can live without affecting each other and your system. Be aware that pip and conda are not equivalent, conda does much more than pip . Conda has at least three different advantages compared to pip. It can managed dependencies and save you from dependency hell.  It can install multiple version of Python whereas pip works with existing version of Python on your system. It can also install non-Python software dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-wrappers&#34;&gt;Code wrappers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An often overlooked advantage of Python is its readability. Python code is said to be almost like pseudo code. The basics of a programming language can be learnt in a considerably small amount of time. A big chunk of time is spent understanding the code written by others and troubleshooting it&amp;rsquo;s usage. Time is mostly spend in discussion forums like stackoverflow to understand the error messages spit out by the code you are trying to fix and seeing other people’s solutions. This is one place where Python&amp;rsquo;s readability shines. One possible downside of it&amp;rsquo;s readbility is that Python is slower than other languages such as C, Fortran etc. However the situation is not very bad since there exists a lot of Python wrapper code that just provides an interface for code written in a faster language. This is very often encountered in machine learning where a lot of the actual heavy lifting is done by faster languages like C and C++.  We pass inputs to the code written in Python, the processing is done by code written is a faster language and finally passed back to the calling python function. A popular example is OpenCV where the python code exists to pass data and arguments to underlying C++ code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;setting-up-your-computer&#34;&gt;Setting up your computer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need a computer at two different stages of your machine learning journey - one while developing your code and one for the training of your ML algorithms. People use ordinary systems for developing code and delegate the training to much powerful workstations or servers. If you do not have access to such powerful hardware do not worry, there are free and paid options available that are much better than owning your own hardware. For code development, if you have the budget to own a laptop with a dedicated graphics card, make sure you only choose laptops that supports the NVIDIA GPUs. But it is not strictly required to own a beefy system. Even a machine which has just an Intel i3 processor or its Ryzen equivalent and a 4GB RAM would suffice. If your laptop comes preinstalled with Windows, try to get it to dual boot a Linux OS. Linux is your best friend when it comes to the world of code development. The term Linux doesn&amp;rsquo;t refer to any particular OS that you can install. However there are various flavours or distributions of Linux which you can actually install on your machine. Ubuntu is one of the most popular Linux distributions. However if you are looking for something more interesting than Ubuntu, ArchLinux based distributions like Endeavour OS are a good option. The Arch User Repository or (AUR) is one of the best features of Arch Linux that makes it easy for beginners to install several packages that are most often missing from official Linux repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;tools-of-the-trade&#34;&gt;Tools of the Trade&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;text-editor-or-ide&#34;&gt;Text editor or IDE&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of very first decision we need to make is regarding how to write and run the code. The simplest and most elegant way to write code is as a script (text file with .py extension) that is run from a terminal program. An IDE or integrated development environment is a much more sophisticated code editor. One of the popular IDEs is jupyterlab or jupyter notebook which is a web browser based IDE. The name is an acronym for Julia, Python and R - the three languages which it supports. What is special about this is it that it provides a way to store the history or sequence of outputs that were generated when the code was run. Hence it is an excellent teaching tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;essential-libraries-for-the-astrophysicist&#34;&gt;Essential libraries for the Astrophysicist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NumPy - One of the most essential packages or libraries that extends Python by adding the ndarray or N-dimensional array datatype and a host of associated functions for manipulating them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pandas - Tabular data is not strictly numerical data but a mix of numerical and string data. Especially we would like to index value from tables using column names which are strings. Pandas adds support for tabular data using the DataFrame datatype.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matplotlib - A rich library that has functions for almost any kind of data visualization that you can imagine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PIL - Python Imaging Library allows you to read data from images stored on your disk to NumPy arrays. It has lots of functions designed to work on images that can supplements NumPy&amp;rsquo;s matrix manipulation functions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scipy - Library of functions for scientific use like special functions, statistical distributions, signal processing etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Astropy - Library of functions for astronomy related uses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;popular-librariesplatformsframeworks-for-ml&#34;&gt;Popular Libraries/Platforms/Frameworks for ML&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scikit-learn - Library of utility functions and implementations of traditional ML algorithms like RandomForest, SVM, MLP etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving on to deep learning techniques, Python has two frameworks for deep learning Tensorflow (aka Tensorflow/Keras) and PyTorch. These are called called platforms or frameworks rather than libraries because these are whole systems rather than just a library of functions. Depending on your choice there will be a lot of change in the way your code will be written and run. Tensorflow was initially developed by Google whereas PyTorch by Facebook. You might now be left hanging with a question - Which one to choose? Personally I find PyTorch better for the beginner. It has a bigger library of predefined model architectures which makes sure hat the beginner is not subjected to the pain of implementing complex network architectures by themselves. At the same time in certain places the lack of a single functions that abstracts away all the complexities of  a model fitting process does good to the beginner in that he gets to know the inner working of the deep learning workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;where-to-get-more-help&#34;&gt;Where to get more help?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this section I will list resources you can use to learn about the things that has been already discussed and more things to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scipylectures - Getting started with Python and learning scientific packages like Numpy, Matplotlib and Scipy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;exercism - A website for learning the basics of Python using exercises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pyimagesearch  - Adrian&amp;rsquo;s blog for Computer Vision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book: Machine Learning: An Algorithmic Perspective - by Stephen Marsland which comes with lot of Python example code for implementing traditional ML algorithms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book: Deep Learning with Python - Introduction to Deep Learning using Python and the Keras framework by the founder of the Keras framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;googlecolab - Free resource for developing and/or training ML models. Jupyter notebook running on a virtual machine in the cloud. Note that a single code can run only upto a maximum of 12 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tensorflow tutorials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;coursera  &amp;amp; udacity - Machine Learning Courses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>AI over coffee</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/posts/ai_over_coffee/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2024 09:51:42 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/posts/ai_over_coffee/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;This article is a coffee table discussion between two friends, Annie and Marty. Annie is an inquisitive learner who just met her long-time friend Marty, who is doing his PhD. in artificial intelligence. Annie is amused by the sudden rise of Artificial Intelligence and wants to understand the underlying concepts or principles that drive its development. She also wants to be abreast of the developments in the field that have led to the current state of affairs. The conversation is divided into sections for the reader to follow along easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-dumb-and-powerful-computers-of-the-past&#34;&gt;The dumb and powerful computers of the past&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Hi Marty. Can you explain to me what this whole A.I. thing is? What is all the buzz about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Ya sure. We are probably on the brink of another industrial revolution. The invention of the steam engine is considered to have brought about the first industrial revolution. The invention of electricity was another big step that radically changed the nature of machines. The invention of the transistor marked the third industrial revolution, or what we call the digital revolution. These transistors power the I.C.s or chips found in most electronics nowadays, including modern computers. The new revolution we are talking about has to do with the age of intelligent machines, and A.I., as you might know, stands for Artificial Intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Oh! Intelligent machines, so that&amp;rsquo;s what it is about. But I was under the impression that computers were already pretty intelligent. I saw this movie recently, ``The Imitation Game&amp;quot;, where they talk about the history of computers and how they were developed during the Second World War era to break the secret code used by the Germans. Is that true?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Yes, it is very accurate. It is also true that the computers of yesteryears were indeed very capable. They have helped astronauts land on the moon, enabled metrologists to predict the weather, and cosmologists to simulate the universe&amp;rsquo;s evolution. As late as 1997, a chess-playing computer called Deep Blue was developed, which beat the reigning world champion Gary Kasparov in his own game. But all of these were done using brute-force techniques and not by intelligent machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;new-age-computers-that-can-learn&#34;&gt;New-Age computers that can learn&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Oh yeah, I remember hearing about Deep Blue beating Kasparov in the news. So do you mean to say that it was not an intelligent computer that did that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: So what are these intelligent machines capable of doing that the previous-generation computers couldn&amp;rsquo;t?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Even the most sophisticated machines of the previous generation failed spectacularly at tasks that even a five-year-old kid could do. These are things like image recognition, speech recognition, and natural language processing. Today&amp;rsquo;s machines are considered intelligent because they are able to do a lot of such tasks that were considered too hot to handle for the older generation of computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Oh burn! So how do the new-age computers shine where previous-generation computers failed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Traditional computers were powerful because of two significant things - brute strength and explicit algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brute strength of the computer comes from its mind-boggling speed;  the modern computer is capable of executing about 5 billion instructions per second, and it&amp;rsquo;s able to crunch large numbers for hours on end without tiring out or getting brain fatigued. An algorithm is something like that recipe you use for cooking a Shakshouka. A set of rules or instructions given to the computer to solve a specific problem. When it is written out in a language that the computer can understand, we call it computer code. With new-age computers, however, we don&amp;rsquo;t need such algorithms. Instead, we have something called learning algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: So why are learning algorithms important for creating intelligent machines?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: If we only had computers that relied on explicit algorithms, that would mean that computers could only solve problems that humans knew how to solve in the first place. When it comes to intelligence, you see that although human intelligence has a lot to do with evolution and our genes, one defining characteristic of intelligence is the ability to learn from experience. A child&amp;rsquo;s brain is somewhat of a clean slate that has just the ability to learn from its environment, hard-wired into it. Everything else that makes it intelligent is learned during the course of its life, either from its own experiences or from the experiences of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: But even if they could achieve these tasks, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t that make these computers only as bright as a five-year-old?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;ai-in-science-and-engineering&#34;&gt;A.I. in science and engineering&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: You may be wrong about that. The ability to learn, paired with the brute strength of computers, results in a deadly combination. Learning to do even the most mundane tasks that people do every day can spark a revolution. The reason for all these fancy applications and the hype that A.I. has been generating recently has to do with people trying to build learning capabilities in their respective domains. Self-driving cars, language translators, spam detection, recommendation engines, etc., are all such examples. But the same techniques can be applied in scientific research, leading to even more exciting applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Ohh. Using A.I. for research? That sounds exciting. What are the research problems that can be tackled using A.I.?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Glad you asked. There are lots of such applications. For instance, in medical research, they are used for cancer diagnosis. Using C.T. scans from both people identified with cancer and similar scans from healthy people, an intelligent machine can be trained to identify patterns in the data that evade even the best oncologists. A.I. is used for drug discovery to identify new drug candidates and predict how they will interact with biological systems. A.I. systems have been used to analyze large amounts of genetic data to identify genetic variants associated with specific diseases and predict an individual&amp;rsquo;s risk of developing a disease. A key part of such research involves the 3D structure identification of proteins from their 2D images, and A.I. is used to do exactly that. In astrophysics, you might remember that the Nobel prize was given for the discovery of gravitational waves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Yeah I remember that. Those were theoretically predicted by Albert Einstein but not observed until recently, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Yes. And even there, A.I. was used to identify the true signals buried under a lot of noise. They are also used to analyze large amounts of telescope data to study the properties of stars, galaxies, and other celestial objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;primitive-learning-algorithms&#34;&gt;Primitive learning algorithms&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Wow. All these sound exciting. So if these &amp;ldquo;learning algorithms&amp;rdquo;  are the workhorses behind all of these things that A.I. is capable of achieving, what are they actually, and how do they work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Instead of having domain-specific rules hard-coded into the machines, the learning algorithms enable computers to make blunders, evaluate the cost of their errors by comparing them with true values, and keep on iterating until the accuracy becomes sufficiently high. In most of these cases, the computers try to arrive at rules by finding patterns in the data shown to them. Remember those questions that often come up in competitive exams where a number is omitted from a sequence of numbers, and we are asked to predict the missing one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Yup. Those are really hard at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Ya. But those are a piece of cake if you use learning algorithms to solve them. The curve fitting you learn in mathematics is an example of such a learning algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Isn&amp;rsquo;t curve fitting what we do when you take observations on graph paper during a science experiment and later try to fit a curve that accommodates all these data points?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: So are these the kind of algorithms that A.I. nowadays uses?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Actually, curve-fitting is one of the simplest and most primitive learning algorithms. Many years of research in this field have led to better learning algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: But what do you mean by a better algorithm?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Curve-fitting is mostly used in cases where the form of the relationship between the variables is known a priori. Most often than not, it is used in cases where the relationship is linear. Additionally, these methods are sensitive to the presence of outliers or noise in the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;artificial-neural-networks&#34;&gt;Artificial Neural Networks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: So what better algorithms have people come up with until now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: The state-of-the-art in artificial intelligence is what we call artificial neural networks or ANN. It is a kind of bio-mimicry where the algorithm is derived from the working of the human brain, which is basically a large network of neurons. Although our knowledge about the brain is quite limited, the general idea we have is that the learning process in the brain is related to what we call neuroplasticity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: And what do you mean by neuroplasticity in our brains?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Our brain is a large collection of neurons. The term &amp;ldquo;large&amp;rdquo; would be an oversimplification; typically, there are about 100 billion neurons with about 100 trillion synapses, which are the connections between the neurons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Wow! That&amp;rsquo;s such a mind-boggling number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Yes it is. Each time a child sees an image, say that of a dog, some of these neurons fire together. The neurons that fire together become well-connected. The connection strength between certain other neurons might decrease. In this way, the idea of a dog is stored in our brain in the strength of the synapses between individual neurons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Oh. So that is probably the reason why different areas of the brain store different memories and have different functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Yes. And as more and more data about dogs comes in through images, the brain can learn a very strong pattern that will enable it to identify all kinds of dogs in the future, even those it hasn&amp;rsquo;t seen yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: So why does my one-year-old nephew mistake the moon for a ball?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Yes. That can happen in the initial phases of development when the brain is slowly learning to identify certain features that can help it to distinguish between objects. As more and more data flows into the brain, it can identify objects at a distance and quickly conclude that it&amp;rsquo;s more probable to be something in the sky rather than a ball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Oh, this conversation has been very interesting. When can we talk more about this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Soon enough I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annie&lt;/strong&gt;: Then it&amp;rsquo;s a bye for now. Bye, Marty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marty&lt;/strong&gt;: Bye Annie.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Understanding Support Vector Machines</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/posts/svm/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 18:24:45 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/posts/svm/</guid>
		<description>\[
\begin{aligned}
KL(\hat{y} || y) &amp;= \sum_{c=1}^{M}\hat{y}_c \log{\frac{\hat{y}_c}{y_c}} \\
JS(\hat{y} || y) &amp;= \frac{1}{2}(KL(y||\frac{y+\hat{y}}{2}) + KL(\hat{y}||\frac{y+\hat{y}}{2}))
\end{aligned}
\]
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Social Media Links</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/personal/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 17:29:48 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/personal/</guid>
		<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://trakt.tv/users/linnabraham&#34;&gt;Trakt.tv&lt;/a&gt; - Movies I have watched&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/grwidget/&#34;&gt;Bookshelf&lt;/a&gt; - Books I have read&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/grwidget_reading/&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/a&gt; - Books I am currently reading&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/list?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;sort=date_added&#34;&gt;Quotes&lt;/a&gt; - that are my favourite&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.last.fm/user/linnabraham/library/tracks&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/a&gt; - that I listen to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Research Notes</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/notes/research_notes/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 12:59:42 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/notes/research_notes/</guid>
		<description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.astropy.org/en/stable/io/fits/appendix/faq.html#id16&#34;&gt;I am opening many FITS files in a loop and getting OSError: Too many open files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see how I implemented this fix in my code see this &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/linnabraham/solar/commit/07d8e5760d839082b1d4678905bf1f6ef8ed2a3b&#34;&gt;commit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Learning Python</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/notes/learn_python/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 10:35:09 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/notes/learn_python/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;These are some of my notes on learning python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dictionaries-in-python&#34;&gt;Dictionaries in Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keys are not limited to strings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;best-practices&#34;&gt;Best practices&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;pylint&lt;/code&gt; to catch errors before actually running your code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn how to use &lt;code&gt;argparse&lt;/code&gt; effectively. Scripts written using argparse can even be run inside jupyter-notebooks with slight tweaking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Programming: Academic Resources</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/programming_resources/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 10:13:09 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/selected/programming_resources/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;curated-videos&#34;&gt;Curated videos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QXjU9qTsYCc&#34;&gt;How do computers read code?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLyzOVJj3bHQuloKGG59rS43e29ro7I57J&#34;&gt;Missing Semester&lt;/a&gt; - videos on the Linux shell, Vim, Git, Tmux etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@LukeSmithxyz&#34;&gt;Luke Smith&amp;rsquo;s Channel&lt;/a&gt; - videos on Linux ricing, ArchLinux, Vim, LaTeX and life advice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/7jiPeIFXb6U&#34;&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like notebooks&lt;/a&gt; - jupytercon presentation made by Joel Grus, AI researcher at Allen AI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;book-recommendations&#34;&gt;Book Recommendations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Books I have read atleast partly and found to be good&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lectures.scientific-python.org/&#34;&gt;Scientific Python Lectures&lt;/a&gt; - A self contained introduction to Python and associated packages for scientific purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Hitchhikers-Guide-Python-Practices-Development/dp/1491933178/&#34;&gt;The Hitchhiker&amp;rsquo;s Guide to Python: Best Practices for Development&lt;/a&gt; by Kenneth Reitz, Tanya Schlusser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Vim Tips</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/notes/vim_tips/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 15:04:48 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/notes/vim_tips/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;default-features-of-vim&#34;&gt;Default features of ViM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;vimdiff&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;support for scp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-useful-plugins-to-use-with-vim&#34;&gt;Some useful plugins to use with ViM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gruvbox - A better colortheme than the default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;markdown-preview - Preview markdown in vim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vimtex - Use vim as LaTeX editor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vim-gnupg - Handle gpg encrypted files easily with vim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Today I found out</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/today_i_found/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 13:44:53 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/today_i_found/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;june-24th-2024&#34;&gt;June 24th, 2024&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; there is a possibility that you accidently kill your sessions by using &lt;code&gt;ctrl-d&lt;/code&gt; instead&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Git and related concepts</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/notes/git_and_related/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 12:40:39 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/notes/git_and_related/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;basic-usage&#34;&gt;Basic usage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;diff&#34;&gt;diff&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See my notes on &lt;a href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/notes/understanding_diff/&#34;&gt;Understanding Diff&lt;/a&gt;.
To see the changes that are brought about by a particular commit in git, do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git diff &amp;lt;parent-commit&amp;gt;..&amp;lt;current-commit&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;staging&#34;&gt;staging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The changes that you to immediately make to your git tracked files are always in the &lt;code&gt;unstaged&lt;/code&gt; state. To stage them, you need to use the &lt;code&gt;git add&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;commit&#34;&gt;commit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You associate a group of changes, possibly to multiple files, to a &lt;code&gt;hash&lt;/code&gt; value. You also associate this &lt;code&gt;hash&lt;/code&gt; with a commit message for it to make sense to you why you made these changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;rebase&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rebase&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say that you have cloned a github repo to two different machines. You work on one and push changes back to the remote (github). When you do the same from the other machine you might run into a &lt;code&gt;merge&lt;/code&gt; conflict. To solve this, you would have to &lt;code&gt;pull&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;--rebase&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;merge&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;merge&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different merge strategies like &lt;code&gt;fast-forward&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;recursive&lt;/code&gt; etc. For non-divergent branches, the default is &lt;code&gt;fast-forward&lt;/code&gt;. This is the case when your local branch has no commits that are not there in the remote branch. For divergent branches, the default strategy is &lt;code&gt;recursive&lt;/code&gt;.
The &lt;code&gt;git pull&lt;/code&gt; command  is basically doing a &lt;code&gt;git fetch&lt;/code&gt; and a &lt;code&gt;git merge&lt;/code&gt; combined.
If you do not want to do a recursive merge, you can use &lt;code&gt;git merge --ff-only&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;git pull --ff-only&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;restore&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;restore&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a dangerous command that you need to handle with caution.
This is often used to replace your unstaged changes with a commited version etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;stash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;stash&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use this to stash away uncommitted changes. Often needed when using &lt;code&gt;git pull --rebase&lt;/code&gt;.
Stash also has an option to save untracked files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;advanced-usage&#34;&gt;Advanced usage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;add---patch&#34;&gt;add &lt;code&gt;--patch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use the &lt;code&gt;git add&lt;/code&gt; command with the &lt;code&gt;-p&lt;/code&gt; option to stage specific hunks from the diff instead of staging all the changes made in a file. If git is not able to split the hunk the way you want there is the &amp;ldquo;e&amp;rdquo; option you can give to manually create a hunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;restore---patch&#34;&gt;restore &lt;code&gt;--patch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restore also supports a patch mode with the &lt;code&gt;-p&lt;/code&gt; flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;amend-and-squash&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;amend&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;squash&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these are basically rebase operations. One difference between them is that &lt;code&gt;amend&lt;/code&gt; only changes the last commit whereas &lt;code&gt;squash&lt;/code&gt; is used to combine multiple commits into single commit. Both are useful for keeping a clean commit history (Read more in the official git &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Tools-Rewriting-History&#34;&gt;docs&lt;/a&gt;).
Once you are familiar with the concepts you can start using &lt;code&gt;--fixup&lt;/code&gt; commits and &lt;code&gt;--autosquash&lt;/code&gt; flags in &lt;code&gt;rebase -i&lt;/code&gt; to speed up things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tags&#34;&gt;tags&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Useful when you want to tag your commits with a version number or name or something. Commit messages are often meant to describe the changes that were made. But when you want to associate
a commit with a working version, tags are helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;git-prompt&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git-prompt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/git/git/blob/master/contrib/completion/git-prompt.sh&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git-prompt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; script provided by git somwhere in your machine and source it in your shell.
After than you can customize your default prompt to show basic git information. Check the comments in the script for usage instruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;optional-usage&#34;&gt;Optional usage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;submodules&#34;&gt;submodules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is useful when you want to nest a git repo inside another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;github-actions&#34;&gt;Github actions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allows you to have workflows attached to your git push commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;pitfalls-to-avoid-when-using-git&#34;&gt;Pitfalls to avoid when using Git&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;having-faithful-commits&#34;&gt;Having faithful commits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a working version of a code. Don&amp;rsquo;t keep modifications that are uncommitted in your staging area. You can use &lt;code&gt;git stash&lt;/code&gt; for this purpose.
Once you have a clean repo &lt;code&gt;tag&lt;/code&gt; the last commit as the one that has the working version. This is useful if you ever want to revist the state of your repo.
If you have unmodified code lying around and some of those code are direct or indirect dependencies in your primary code you never know what was the actual state of your repo when you commited it. The commit are no longer a faithful representation.
This is also where you should start thinking of version controlling your data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-not-to-lose-your-data-while-learning-git&#34;&gt;How not to lose your data while learning git&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a beginner who wants to try out certain git commands on your repo but afraid that you might lose data (you should be), then you have two options. Certain commands in git would have an associated &lt;code&gt;dry-run&lt;/code&gt; option. Check for that in the docs. If there is no such option then a fail safe alternative is to just create a test branch from your current branch. Test out the things there and once you are satisified, repeat it on the master. Then simply delete the test branch.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Software I Use</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/software_i_use/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 12:19:50 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/software_i_use/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;I use Linux as my primary operating system. The flavour of Linux that I use is &lt;a href=&#34;https://archlinux.org/&#34;&gt;ArchLinux&lt;/a&gt;. Which is great on multiple counts. One, it follows a minimalist approach of giving you only the bare minimum packages and configurations by default. Two, it is a rolling release which means that you get the updates for all the packages you have installed, as soon as they are published. The third reason is the presence of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aur.archlinux.org/&#34;&gt;AUR&lt;/a&gt; (Arch User Repository) which enables you to install a lot of niche packages with just a single command. All the complicated stuff like the download and configuration are taken care of for you under-the-hood.
If you want to get a taste of ArchLinux without installing and configuring everything from scratch (like you should be doing), &lt;a href=&#34;https://endeavouros.com/&#34;&gt;EndeavourOS&lt;/a&gt; is a good one to try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;desktop-environment&#34;&gt;Desktop Environment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not use any of the full fledged desktop environments (DE) like &lt;code&gt;Gnome&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;KDE&lt;/code&gt;. Rather  I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/I3&#34;&gt;i3&lt;/a&gt; which is just a tiling window manager. Until recently I was using &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Openbox&#34;&gt;Openbox&lt;/a&gt; which was a floating window manager. Using just a window manager means that you get to pick and choose and build your own desktop environment. My desktop environment includes the following apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Polybar&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;polybar&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as my status bar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Dunst&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;dunst&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for my notifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Xcompmgr&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xcompmgr&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for window effects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Dmenu&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;dmenu&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as my application switcher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Sxhkd&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sxhkd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for keyboard shortcuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click here for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/linnabraham/dotfiles-primary&#34;&gt;primary dotfiles&lt;/a&gt; and here for dotfiles for my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/linnabraham/dotfiles-iucaa-arch&#34;&gt;office machine&lt;/a&gt;.
Here is a collection of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/linnabraham/useful-scripts&#34;&gt;useful scripts&lt;/a&gt; that I use as part of my setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;common-applications-that-i-use&#34;&gt;Common Applications that I use&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Music player - &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Music_Player_Daemon&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;mpd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SoongNoonien/plattenalbum&#34;&gt;plattenablum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video player - &lt;code&gt;mpv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Browser - &lt;code&gt;brave&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text editor - &lt;code&gt;gvim&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pdf viewer - &lt;code&gt;evince&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code editor - &lt;a href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/notes/vim_tips/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Terminal emulator - &lt;code&gt;xfce4-terminal&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Image viewer - &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Sxiv&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;sxiv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graphical file manager - &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lxqt/pcmanfm-qt&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pcmanfm-qt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remote desktop management - &lt;a href=&#34;https://rustdesk.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rustdesk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;research-related-applications&#34;&gt;Research related applications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Academic document preparation - &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/TeX_Live&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;texlive&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reference management - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;zotero&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;special-purpose-applications&#34;&gt;Special-purpose applications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bookmark management - &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jarun/buku&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;buku&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Terminal file-manager - &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Lf&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;lf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Terminal image preview - &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ueber-devel/ueberzug&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ueberzug&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calendar management - &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pimutils/khal&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;khal&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pimutils/vdirsyncer&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vdirsyncer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Password management - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.passwordstore.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pass&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/carnager/rofi-pass&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rofi-pass&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Music metadata management - &lt;a href=&#34;https://musicbrainz.org/doc/MusicBrainz_Picard&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;musicbrainz picard&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Backup management - &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Btrfs&#34;&gt;btrfs&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/snapper&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;snapper&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dotfiles management - &lt;a href=&#34;https://yadm.io/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;yadm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;low-level-configurations&#34;&gt;Low-level configurations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;zsh&lt;/code&gt; as my shell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;btrfs&lt;/code&gt; as my filesystem format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;uefi&lt;/code&gt; comptabile bootloader&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;web-services&#34;&gt;Web services&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://omnivore.app/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;omnivore&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as my read-it-later app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amplenote.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;amplenote&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as my note-taking and task-management app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Understanding diff</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/notes/understanding_diff/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 11:45:39 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/notes/understanding_diff/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Q. Do you find it difficult at times to interpret the output of &lt;code&gt;diff foo bar&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. The output shows what changes you need to make to &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt; in order to make it identical to &lt;code&gt;bar&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Lifehacks for a Workaholic</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/notes/lifehacks/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 12:41:17 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/notes/lifehacks/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Life is mostly a game of achieving the best of both worlds (or many worlds).
Here are some of my recommendations for someone who wants to run multiple tasks at a time but also seeks perfection in all that they do.
There is something called the Getting Things Done (GTD) methodology as made famous by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Getting-Things-Done/dp/0143573195&#34;&gt;David Allen&lt;/a&gt; in his book of the same name. If you find the book a bit dry, watch videos by people on youtube like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@aliabdaal&#34;&gt;Ali Abdaal&lt;/a&gt;. Two other interesting books to read are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40121378-atomic-habits&#34;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt; by James Clear and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25744928-deep-work&#34;&gt;Deep Work&lt;/a&gt; by Cal Newport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-amplenote&#34;&gt;Use Amplenote&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amplenote is an app that goes hand in hand with the GTD methodology.
Before coming to Amplenote my workflow involved seperate apps for journalling (Obsidian or Logseq), task-management (Trello or Taskwarrior) and calendar (google calendar).
Amplenote is designed to do all these at the same time and it also has a mobile app that is easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-technique-in-brief&#34;&gt;The technique in brief&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Identify the most important projects that you need to work on based on your values and goals in life.
Keep in mind that what competes with your goals are often, your other goals.
For collaborative projects if you have regular group meetings, create a meeting minutes document where you log the important points that were discussed. Create a condensed version of this in your notes. Turn any actionable item to a task.
Use the calendar blocking technique to block it on your calendar.
Keep a work log for each project where you document the progress you made each day and your thoughts on it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Machine Learning: Software Toolkit</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/toolkit/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 10:34:25 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/selected/toolkit/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;When you start out by doing computer vision problems in Deep Learning, you quickly run into the issue of having to deal with remote machines. Especially one&amp;rsquo;s that have GPU designed for such tasks. When you have to deal with these headless machines that do not have a display or user interface, there is a need to learn a plethora of command line tools that are available on linux.
In order to learn more about the tools that are mentioned below you can watch these set of lectures by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z56Jmr9Z34Q&amp;amp;list=PLyzOVJj3bHQuloKGG59rS43e29ro7I57J&#34;&gt;Missing Semester&lt;/a&gt; or follow &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@LukeSmithxyz&#34;&gt;Luke Smith&lt;/a&gt; on youtube. Some of these tools have a big learning curve. Which is the price you pay in order to reap the rewards in the long term. However if you are someone who just wants to get things done and move along or are short of time. I will give alternate suggestions wherever applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tools-that-are-useful-for-anyone&#34;&gt;Tools That are Useful for Anyone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ssh&#34;&gt;SSH&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the very first ones would be &lt;strong&gt;SSH&lt;/strong&gt; which helps you to login to a remote machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;vim&#34;&gt;ViM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very next need is a text editor that can run entirely in your terminal without needing a UI. On Linux, you can choose from ViM, Nano, emacs or mcedit. Oh, if you are one of those persons who can never let go of the jupyter-notebook IDE. And would prefer running code on the remote machine using jupyter-notebooks, I would recommend you watch this video &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7jiPeIFXb6U&#34;&gt;I dont like notebooks&lt;/a&gt; by AllenAI researcher Joel Grus. If you are short on time you can instead explore the VSCode IDE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;git&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git is the modern code version control software. It is one of Linus Torvalds contributions to open source that he believes has an even greater impact than the Linux kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;screen-or-tmux&#34;&gt;Screen or Tmux&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Code for deep learning takes hours or even days to run. Although the remote server can remain switched on all the time, you do not want your laptop switched on all the time. When you disconnect your ssh connection or close the current terminal, you kill all associated programs that are running. How do you keep them running even when you close your terminal and log out of the client machine (your laptop)? Using programs like &lt;code&gt;screen&lt;/code&gt; or its modern variant &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conda&#34;&gt;Conda&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conda can be installed through either of the distributions Anaconda or Miniconda. Conda might be frustrating at time with the time taken to install packages. Use conda to install mamba and then use mamba in place of conda for all package installations. There are times when you might have to use pip. For example when the package is not there in conda. Or you need to install a package directly from it&amp;rsquo;s git version. But in all other cases you are much better off using conda for environment management because it can version control non Python software as well. You often require non Python software for compiling python packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;research-reading--writing&#34;&gt;Research Reading &amp;amp; Writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use markdown files for quick documentation. There are note editors that can read and render markdown like Obsidian, Logseq, Notion etc. Even ViM has some basic support for markdown. Use LaTeX for academic document preparation. Use Zotero for storing, annotating research papers and exporting the references as a bib file for use in LaTeX citations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;python-related&#34;&gt;Python related&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.python.org/3/library/pdb.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pdb&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - python debugger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.org/project/pylint/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pylint&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - catching basic errors in your code without running the code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pypi.org/project/gdown/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;gdown&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - host small datasets in your google drive and use gdown for creating scripts for downloading them on the go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;machine-learning-specific-tools&#34;&gt;Machine Learning Specific Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tensorflow-of-pytorch&#34;&gt;Tensorflow of PyTorch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both are great frameworks that are being actively developed. One pitfall that I have fallen into is thinking that the framework that makes it easy to write code is the best. This might not always be the case. Maybe it is good for the engineer who is playing with ready made stuff but not so good for the researcher who needs to look into the internals of the code they are running. PyTorch might be a tad better for the beginner than tensorflow in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wandb&#34;&gt;Wandb&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to capture the learning process is important to troubleshoot problems with the learning. You can visualize the training loss in each iteration of your epoch and monitor the validation loss after every epoch. You can also look into how the weights are changing. Or you could use model attribution techniques to create heatmaps etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dvc&#34;&gt;DVC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When working on Machine Learning projects, you do a lot of data processing. Hence for reproducibility you should be able to be version control not just the code but also the data. As an added benefit DVC also lets you version control your model, if you need to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>About this webpage</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/posts/website/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 20:47:07 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/posts/website/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;github-actions&#34;&gt;Github Actions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A website is basically an HTML file on someone else&amp;rsquo;s computer. Once you have this, then you need to have a unique easy-to-remember address to type into the address bar of your browser. This is translated into an IP address by your browser by looking up the number on the yellow pages of the internet, a process which is also called Domain Name Resolution and for which there are dedicated servers known as DNS servers.
Therefore to run a website the minimum you require is a computer and a domain name. Luckily Github provides both to you for free. A computer through &lt;strong&gt;Github Actions&lt;/strong&gt; and a free domain name that includes .github.io.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;hugo-a-static-site-generator&#34;&gt;Hugo, A static-site generator&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown is a text formatting language invented by none other than the legendary Aaron Swartz. Instead of directly writing in html, you get to write in markdown and have software convert it into html.
&lt;strong&gt;Hugo&lt;/strong&gt; is software that does this among other things. CSS is a language that was invented to stylize the content of your website.
Hugo also generates CSS files that does the beautification of your website.
It is also called a static site generator. Create a repository in github that ends with .github.io and clone it in your machine.
Copy the contents of the public folder generated by hugo to this git repo.
When you set up github actions, Github has a computer that serves the content of this repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;theme&#34;&gt;Theme&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme is inspired from &lt;a href=&#34;https://lukesmith.xyz/&#34;&gt;Luke Smith&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Machine Learning: Academic Resources</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/selected/books/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 19:28:06 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/selected/books/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Go here for a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/linnabraham/ml-tutorials/blob/master/Resources.md&#34;&gt;collection of resources&lt;/a&gt; compiled together like a course outline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are books I have read (at least partly) and know to be good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Learning-Python-Second-Fran%C3%A7ois-Chollet/dp/1617296864/&#34;&gt;Deep Learning with Python&lt;/a&gt; by Francois Chollet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pyimagesearch.com/deep-learning-computer-vision-python-book/&#34;&gt;Deep Learning for Computer Vision&lt;/a&gt; by Adrian Rosebrock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Machine-Learning-Algorithmic-Perspective-Recognition/dp/1466583282/&#34;&gt;Machine Learning: An Algorithmic Perspective&lt;/a&gt; by Stephen Marsland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Statistics-Mining-Machine-Learning-Astronomy/dp/0691198306&#34;&gt;Statistics, Data Mining, and Machine Learning in Astronomy&lt;/a&gt; by Željko Ivezić, Andrew J. Connolly , Jacob T. VanderPlas &amp;amp; Alexander Gray&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Deep-Learning-Adaptive-Computation-Machine/dp/0262035618&#34;&gt;Deep Learning &lt;/a&gt; by Ian Goodfellow , Yoshua Bengio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Pattern-Recognition-Learning-Information-Statistics/dp/0387310738/&#34;&gt;Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; by Christopher M. Bishop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are books I believe are great and which I would like to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Information-Theory-Inference-Learning-Algorithms/dp/0521642981&#34;&gt;Information Theory, Inference and Learning Algorithms&lt;/a&gt; by David J. C. MacKay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-Statistical-Learning-Applications-Statistics/dp/3031387465/&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Statistical Learning&lt;/a&gt; by Gareth James, Daniela Witten, Trevor Hastie, Robert Tibshirani &amp;amp; Jonathan Taylor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.in/Artificial-Intelligence-Modern-Approach-4e/dp/9356063575/&#34;&gt;Artificial Intelligence: A Modern Approach&lt;/a&gt; by Stuart Russell &amp;amp; Peter Norvig&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non-book recommendations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Videos by Grant Sanderson from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@3blue1brown&#34;&gt;3Blue1Brown&lt;/a&gt; channel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://karpathy.github.io/&#34;&gt;Andrej Karpathy&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title></title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/grwidget/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/grwidget/</guid>
		<description>      &lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34; media=&#34;screen&#34;&gt;
        .gr_grid_container {
          /* customize grid container div here. eg: width: 500px; */
        }

        .gr_grid_book_container {
          /* customize book cover container div here */
          float: left;
          width: 98px;
          height: 160px;
          padding: 0px 0px;
          overflow: hidden;
        }
      &lt;/style&gt;
      &lt;div id=&#34;gr_grid_widget_1719130852&#34;&gt;
        &lt;!-- Show static html as a placeholder in case js is not enabled - javascript include will override this if things work --&gt;
            &lt;h2&gt;
      &lt;a style=&#34;text-decoration: none;&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/5186783-linn?shelf=read&amp;utm_medium=api&amp;utm_source=grid_widget&#34;&gt;Linn&#39;s bookshelf: read&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h2&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Operation Thunderbolt: Flight 139 and the Raid on Entebbe Airport, the Most Audacious Hostage Rescue Mission in History&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25318813-operation-thunderbolt&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Operation Thunderbolt: Flight 139 and the Raid on Entebbe Airport, the Most Audacious Hostage Rescue Mission in History&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1433450810l/25318813._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;ഖസാക്കിന്റെ ഇതിഹാസം | Khasakkinte Ithihasam | The Legends of Khasak&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2623267-khasakkinte-ithihasam-the-legends-of-khasak&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ഖസാക്കിന്റെ ഇതിഹാസം | Khasakkinte Ithihasam | The Legends of Khasak&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1462709894l/2623267._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Kafka on the Shore&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/4929.Kafka_on_the_Shore&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Kafka on the Shore&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1429638085l/4929._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The Tell-Tale Brain: A Neuroscientist&#39;s Quest for What Makes Us Human&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8574712-the-tell-tale-brain&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Tell-Tale Brain: A Neuroscientist&#39;s Quest for What Makes Us Human&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348750093l/8574712._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Introducing Psychology: A Graphic Guide&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26862950-introducing-psychology&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Introducing Psychology: A Graphic Guide&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1443955316l/26862950._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;ആൽഫ | Alpha&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17910389-alpha&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ആൽഫ | Alpha&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1471277750l/17910389._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23692271-sapiens&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1703329310l/23692271._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Rich Dad Poor Dad: What the Rich Teach Their Kids About Money That the Poor and Middle Class Do Not!&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/39924789-rich-dad-poor-dad&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Rich Dad Poor Dad: What the Rich Teach Their Kids About Money That the Poor and Middle Class Do Not!&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1524451661l/39924789._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The Naked Woman: A Study of the Female Body&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/124663.The_Naked_Woman&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Naked Woman: A Study of the Female Body&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1316727767l/124663._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Eat, Drink, and Be Healthy: The Harvard Medical School Guide to Healthy Eating&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34466919-eat-drink-and-be-healthy&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Eat, Drink, and Be Healthy: The Harvard Medical School Guide to Healthy Eating&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1505658899l/34466919._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25744928-deep-work&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1447957962l/25744928._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Atomic Habits: An Easy &amp; Proven Way to Build Good Habits &amp; Break Bad Ones&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40121378-atomic-habits&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Atomic Habits: An Easy &amp; Proven Way to Build Good Habits &amp; Break Bad Ones&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1655988385l/40121378._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;In Order to Live: A North Korean Girl&#39;s Journey to Freedom&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26063290-in-order-to-live&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;In Order to Live: A North Korean Girl&#39;s Journey to Freedom&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1439054113l/26063290._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The Tales of Beedle the Bard (Hogwarts Library, #3)&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3950967-the-tales-of-beedle-the-bard&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Tales of Beedle the Bard&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1630876355l/3950967._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Man’s Search for Meaning&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/4069.Man_s_Search_for_Meaning&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Man’s Search for Meaning&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1535419394l/4069._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Food Rules: An Eater&#39;s Manual&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7015635-food-rules&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Food Rules: An Eater&#39;s Manual&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348526224l/7015635._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Toxic Parents: Overcoming Their Hurtful Legacy and Reclaiming Your Life&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/103999.Toxic_Parents&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Toxic Parents: Overcoming Their Hurtful Legacy and Reclaiming Your Life&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1320537700l/103999._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;മനുഷ്യരറിയാൻ | Manushyanariyan&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/49994675-manushyanariyan&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;മനുഷ്യരറിയാൻ | Manushyanariyan&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1576505592l/49994675._SX98_SY160_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Free Will&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13180629-free-will&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Free Will&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1332924961l/13180629._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Top 10 for Men&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6090934-top-10-for-men&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Top 10 for Men&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1348802536l/6090934._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;br style=&#34;clear: both&#34;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;gr_grid_branding&#34; style=&#34;font-size: .9em; color: #382110; text-decoration: none; float: right; clear: both&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/5186783-linn&#34;&gt;Linn&#39;s favorite books »&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;noscript&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Share &lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/&#34;&gt;book reviews&lt;/a&gt; and ratings with Linn, and even join a &lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/group&#34;&gt;book club&lt;/a&gt; on Goodreads.&lt;/noscript&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;script src=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/grid_widget/5186783.Linn&#39;s%20bookshelf:%20read?cover_size=medium&amp;hide_link=&amp;hide_title=&amp;num_books=30&amp;order=d&amp;shelf=read&amp;sort=date_read&amp;widget_id=1719130852&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title></title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/grwidget_reading/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/grwidget_reading/</guid>
		<description>
      &lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34; media=&#34;screen&#34;&gt;
        .gr_grid_container {
          /* customize grid container div here. eg: width: 500px; */
        }

        .gr_grid_book_container {
          /* customize book cover container div here */
          float: left;
          width: 98px;
          height: 160px;
          padding: 0px 0px;
          overflow: hidden;
        }
      &lt;/style&gt;
      &lt;div id=&#34;gr_grid_widget_1719897843&#34;&gt;
        &lt;!-- Show static html as a placeholder in case js is not enabled - javascript include will override this if things work --&gt;
            &lt;h2&gt;
      &lt;a style=&#34;text-decoration: none;&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/5186783-linn?shelf=currently-reading&amp;utm_medium=api&amp;utm_source=grid_widget&#34;&gt;Linn&#39;s currently-reading book montage&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h2&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The 48 Laws of Power&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1303.The_48_Laws_of_Power&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The 48 Laws of Power&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1694722764l/1303._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Models: Attract Women Through Honesty&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/12633800-models&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Models: Attract Women Through Honesty&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1375568311l/12633800._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;ആരാച്ചാർ | Aarachar&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/27867186-aarachar&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;ആരാച്ചാർ | Aarachar&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1460223255l/27867186._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;Economic Facts and Fallacies&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2064279.Economic_Facts_and_Fallacies&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Economic Facts and Fallacies&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1322121883l/2064279._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The God Delusion&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/14743.The_God_Delusion&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The God Delusion&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1347220693l/14743._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The Selfish Gene&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/61535.The_Selfish_Gene&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Selfish Gene&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1366758096l/61535._SY160_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The Emperor of All Maladies: A Biography of Cancer&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11482377-the-emperor-of-all-maladies&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Emperor of All Maladies: A Biography of Cancer&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1340886277l/11482377._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;The Sins of the Father&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/15927346-the-sins-of-the-father&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Sins of the Father&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1347994804l/15927346._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;gr_grid_book_container&#34;&gt;&lt;a title=&#34;രണ്ടാമൂഴം | Randamoozham&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2757012-randamoozham&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;രണ്ടാമൂഴം | Randamoozham&#34; border=&#34;0&#34; src=&#34;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1260916398l/2757012._SX98_.jpg&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;br style=&#34;clear: both&#34;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;gr_grid_branding&#34; style=&#34;font-size: .9em; color: #382110; text-decoration: none; float: right; clear: both&#34; rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/5186783-linn&#34;&gt;Linn&#39;s favorite books »&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;noscript&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Share &lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/&#34;&gt;book reviews&lt;/a&gt; and ratings with Linn, and even join a &lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/group&#34;&gt;book club&lt;/a&gt; on Goodreads.&lt;/noscript&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;script src=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/grid_widget/5186783.Linn&#39;s%20currently-reading%20book%20montage?cover_size=medium&amp;hide_link=&amp;hide_title=&amp;num_books=20&amp;order=d&amp;shelf=currently-reading&amp;sort=date_added&amp;widget_id=1719897843&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>About Me</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/about/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/about/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;I am Linn Abraham. I am basically a computer nerd, who also happens to be very passionate about Science.
I am doing a Ph.D.  where I work on solving problems in Astrophysics using Machine Learning.
A few of the problems that I work on are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated galaxy morphology classification using Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prediction of solar flares from Active Region images using Deep Learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detection of HI sources from radio data cubes using 3D CNNs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work on the prediction of solar flares using Deep Learning is part of a JRF Project funded by ISRO. I developed and currently maintain the website for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://suit.iucaa.in&#34;&gt;Solar Ultraviolet Imaging Telescope (SUIT)&lt;/a&gt; along with my teammates in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/The+Inter-University+Centre+for+Astronomy+and+Astrophysics/@18.5592415,73.8253115,3a,75y,90t/data=!3m8!1e2!3m6!1sAF1QipP8MobfPKzfBxsux1HhY-jz_zNzlL24z6G5CHuB!2e10!3e12!6shttps:%2F%2Flh5.googleusercontent.com%2Fp%2FAF1QipP8MobfPKzfBxsux1HhY-jz_zNzlL24z6G5CHuB%3Dw114-h86-k-no!7i4000!8i3000!4m11!1m2!2m1!1sIUCAA!3m7!1s0x3bc2bf45db40022d:0x1efcdd94c3239f51!8m2!3d18.5592415!4d73.8253115!10e5!15sCgVJVUNBQZIBEnJlc2VhcmNoX2luc3RpdHV0ZeABAA!16zL20vMDQ0ODg1?entry=ttu&#34;&gt;IUCAA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://machinelearningmaniac.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; which is a collection of random articles that I write in relation to machine learning and astronomy. This is my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/linnabraham&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; page. You can also connect with me on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/linn-abraham/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested to know me personally check out my &lt;a href=&#34;https://linnabraham.me/personal/&#34;&gt;social media&lt;/a&gt; links.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Quick Links</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/links/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/links/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Hey cool&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	</channel>
</rss>
