<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
	<title>Linn Abraham&#39;s homepage</title>
	<link>https://linnabraham.me/categories/</link>
	<description>Recent content in Categories on Linn Abraham&#39;s homepage</description>
	<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
	<language>en-us</language>
    
        <atom:link href="https://linnabraham.me/categories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	
	
	<item>
		<title>About this webpage</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/posts/website/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 20:47:07 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/posts/website/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;github-actions&#34;&gt;Github Actions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A website is basically an HTML file on someone else&amp;rsquo;s computer. Once you have this, then you need to have a unique easy-to-remember address to type into the address bar of your browser. This is translated into an IP address by your browser by looking up the number on the yellow pages of the internet, a process which is also called Domain Name Resolution and for which there are dedicated servers known as DNS servers.
Therefore to run a website the minimum you require is a computer and a domain name. Luckily Github provides both to you for free. A computer through &lt;strong&gt;Github Actions&lt;/strong&gt; and a free domain name that includes .github.io.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;hugo-a-static-site-generator&#34;&gt;Hugo, A static-site generator&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown is a text formatting language invented by none other than the legendary Aaron Swartz. Instead of directly writing in html, you get to write in markdown and have software convert it into html.
&lt;strong&gt;Hugo&lt;/strong&gt; is software that does this among other things. CSS is a language that was invented to stylize the content of your website.
Hugo also generates CSS files that does the beautification of your website.
It is also called a static site generator. Create a repository in github that ends with .github.io and clone it in your machine.
Copy the contents of the public folder generated by hugo to this git repo.
When you set up github actions, Github has a computer that serves the content of this repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;theme&#34;&gt;Theme&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme is inspired from &lt;a href=&#34;https:lukesmith.xyz/&#34;&gt;Luke Smith&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Machine Learning Resources</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/books/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 19:28:06 +0530</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/books/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;These are books I have read (at least partly) and know to be good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Learning-Python-Second-Fran%C3%A7ois-Chollet/dp/1617296864/&#34;&gt;Deep Learning with Python&lt;/a&gt; by Francois Chollet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Machine-Learning-Algorithmic-Perspective-Recognition/dp/1466583282/&#34;&gt;Machine Learning: An Algorithmic Perspective&lt;/a&gt; by Stephen Marsland&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Statistics-Mining-Machine-Learning-Astronomy/dp/0691198306&#34;&gt;Statistics, Data Mining, and Machine Learning in Astronomy&lt;/a&gt; by Željko Ivezić, Andrew J. Connolly , Jacob T. VanderPlas &amp;amp; Alexander Gray&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Deep-Learning-Adaptive-Computation-Machine/dp/0262035618&#34;&gt;Deep Learning &lt;/a&gt; by Ian Goodfellow , Yoshua Bengio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Pattern-Recognition-Learning-Information-Statistics/dp/0387310738/&#34;&gt;Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; by Christopher M. Bishop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are books I believe are great and which I would like to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Information-Theory-Inference-Learning-Algorithms/dp/0521642981&#34;&gt;Information Theory, Inference and Learning Algorithms&lt;/a&gt; by David J. C. MacKay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-Statistical-Learning-Applications-Statistics/dp/3031387465/&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Statistical Learning&lt;/a&gt; by Gareth James, Daniela Witten, Trevor Hastie, Robert Tibshirani &amp;amp; Jonathan Taylor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>About Me</title>
		<link>https://linnabraham.me/about/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://linnabraham.me/about/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;I am Linn Abraham. I am basically a computer nerd, who also happens to be very passionate about Science.
I am doing a Ph.D.  where I work on solving problems in Astrophysics using Machine Learning.
A few of the problems that I work on are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automated galaxy morphology classification using Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prediction of solar flares from Active Region images using Deep Learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detection of HI sources from radio data cubes using 3D CNNs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work on the prediction of solar flares using Deep Learning is part of a JRF Project funded by ISRO. I developed and currently maintain the website for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://suit.iucaa.in&#34;&gt;Solar Ultraviolet Imaging Telescope (SUIT)&lt;/a&gt; along with my teammates in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/The+Inter-University+Centre+for+Astronomy+and+Astrophysics/@18.5592415,73.8253115,3a,75y,90t/data=!3m8!1e2!3m6!1sAF1QipP8MobfPKzfBxsux1HhY-jz_zNzlL24z6G5CHuB!2e10!3e12!6shttps:%2F%2Flh5.googleusercontent.com%2Fp%2FAF1QipP8MobfPKzfBxsux1HhY-jz_zNzlL24z6G5CHuB%3Dw114-h86-k-no!7i4000!8i3000!4m11!1m2!2m1!1sIUCAA!3m7!1s0x3bc2bf45db40022d:0x1efcdd94c3239f51!8m2!3d18.5592415!4d73.8253115!10e5!15sCgVJVUNBQZIBEnJlc2VhcmNoX2luc3RpdHV0ZeABAA!16zL20vMDQ0ODg1?entry=ttu&#34;&gt;IUCAA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://machinelearningmaniac.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; which is a collection of random articles that I write in relation to machine learning and astronomy. This is my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/linnabraham&#34;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; page. You can also connect with me on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/linn-abraham/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the movies I watched recently &lt;a href=&#34;https://trakt.tv/users/linnabraham&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Here are some of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/5186783?shelf=read&#34;&gt;books&lt;/a&gt; that I have read and enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	</channel>
</rss>
